Guide to the Women's Studies Program records, 1981-2008 (bulk 1981-2002) UA.25.41.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Women's Studies Program records
1981-2008 (bulk 1981-2002)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University Women's Studies Program
UA.25.41.0001
35 Linear Feet
The Women's Studies Program at Duke University started in 1983 and grew rapidly into one of the largest interdisciplinary programs at the University, now called Gender, Sexuality, and Feminist Studies. The Women's Studies Program Records contain materials related to the foundation, growth, activities, and alumni of the Women's Studies Program.
Access Restrictions
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use of administrative records. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist. Contact Research Services for more information.
Provenance
Transfer, 1984-2004
Accessions: UA1988-14, UA1989-27. UA1989-61, UA1990-113, UA1990-22, UA1990-74, UA1991-20, UA1992-96, UA1993-12, UA1993-17, UA1993-39, UA1994-87, UA1994-89, 1995-107, UA1995-65, UA1996-88, UA1997-33, UA1998-65, UA1999-59, UA2001-3, UA2002-60, UA2003-11, UA2004-67
Historical Note
The Women's Studies Program at Duke University started in 1983 with "a single desk in the corner of 119 East Duke", and grew rapidly into one of the largest interdisciplinary programs at the University, now called Gender, Sexuality, and Feminist Studies.
Beginning in 1983, Women's Studies offered an undergraduate certification and sought to bring scholarship on women and gender issues into the curriculum across Trinity College. From 1984 to 1990, Women's Studies offered "mainstreaming grants," awards given to Duke faculty to develop and teach classes in their own areas of specialty that included women and women's roles and accomplishments in transformative ways. Graduate courses were first offered in 1987, with the first Graduate Research Conference held in 1990, organized by and focusing on graduate students and their work. An undergraduate major was first granted in 1994. In 1998, Jean O'Barr was named the Margaret Taylor Smith Director, believed to be the nation's first endowed director's chair in women's studies, founded in large part by alumna Margaret Taylor Smith. Jean O'Barr stepped down as director in 2001, and was followed by Robyn Wiegman until 2007, Ranjana Khanna until 2015, Priscilla Wald until 2019, and Jolie Olcott. In 2016, the name of the program was changed to Gender, Sexuality, and Feminist Studies.
An Advisory Board was formed in 1984 to assist the director in considering the goals of the program, planning faculty activities, and promoting the program widely. The Board consisted of the program director, several faculty members, and staff including a reference librarian and others. The Advisory Board was renamed the Steering Committee in 1991. In 1985, Jean O'Barr began discussions with administrators about forming a friend's group for the Women's Studies Program, and in 1986 the Council on Women's Studies was formed to increase the Program's visibility, provide advice, and fundraise. Judy Woodruff served as the first chair of the Council, which consisted of alumni and friends of Duke and Women's Studies.
Sources: "History", Gender, Sexuality, and Feminist Studies website, https://gendersexualityfeminist.duke.edu/about/history, accessed 2019 July 24.
Collection Overview
The Women's Studies Program Records contain materials related to the foundation, growth, activities, and alumni of the Women's Studies Program. Included are correspondence, minutes, reports, newsletters, flyers, budgets, programs, surveys, and many other materials. Topics include the development of the Women's Studies Program from a certificate program to an undergraduate major and minor as well as the growth of graduate scholarship; the curriculum of the Program and the inclusion of women's studies and women's topics in other areas of the University; outreach to and fundraising with Duke alumni women and others; programs and events organized by Women's Studies, especially the Graduate Research Conference and other large conferences hosted by Women's Studies; the work of the Council on Women's Studies; and a survey given to all women alumni of Duke from the 1920s through the 1980s including questions related to their Duke experience, activities since graduation, and perspective on women's issues, among many other subjects. The majority of the materials date from Jean O'Barr's tenure as director of Women's Studies.
Conditions Governing Access
Records of the University's Board of Trustees which have been in existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees. Contact Research Services for more information.
Conditions Governing Access
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Conditions Governing Access
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of audiotapes and videotapes from this collection requires the creation of reference copies. Reference copies for some materials may have been made, and if a reference copy exists, it is noted in this finding aid. To arrange for the creation of reference copies of other items, please contact University Archives staff. Although these recordings are now stored in a stable environment, their condition and playback quality is unknown.
Conditions Governing Access
Electronic records in this collection have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use these records.
Women's studies -- Study and teaching; Women's studies -- Curricula -- North Carolina; Women's studies -- Research; Women college students -- North Carolina; Curriculum planning; Duke University. Women's Studies Program; Duke University--Students; Duke University -- Graduate students; Duke University -- Faculty; O'Barr, Jean F.; Duke University -- Funds and scholarships; Duke University -- Alumni and alumnae
- Administrative Materials, 1981-2008; 1
  Scope and Contents
  The Administrative Materials series of the Women's Studies Program records contains materials related to the formation, operation, activities, students, staff, finances, and projects of the Women's Studies Program. Included are correspondence, minutes, reports, newsletters, flyers, budgets, programs, and many other materials.
  The series is organized into seven subseries: Advisory Board/Steering Committee, the guiding administrative group of Women's Studies; Curriculum, related to the development and revision of the Women's Studies curriculum; General and Subject Files, covering a wide variety of topics related to the operation of Women's Studies; Financial Materials, related to budgets and fundraising; Personnel Materials, related to the staff and faculty of Women's Studies; Newsletters, produced by Women's Studies for the alumni, friends, and the wider public; and Special Projects, related to large-scale projects created or coordinated by Women's Studies.
  Topics of note in this series include the development of the Women's Studies Program from a certificate program to an undergraduate major and minor as well as the growth of graduate scholarship, in the Advisory Board/Steering Committee and General and Subject Files subseries; the search for joint faculty appointments between Women's Studies and other disciplines, in the Personnel subseries; and large projects including the Women in Science and Engineering Project, in Special Projects.
  Conditions Governing Access
  For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use of administrative records. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist. Contact Research Services for more information.
  Records of the University's Board of Trustees which have been in existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees. Contact Research Services for more information.
  In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
  - Advisory Board/Steering Committee, 1984-1999; 1.1
    The Advisory Board and Steering Committee subseries of the Administrative Materials series contains materials related to the formation, membership, and activities of the guiding administrative group of the Women's Studies Program. Included are correspondence, minutes, notes, memorandum, and other materials related to the long-range planning, development, growth, and administration of the Women's Studies Program. Topics include curriculum development, faculty, fundraising, and many other subjects.
    - Advisory Board, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Advisory Board, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Advisory Board, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - Advisory Board, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Advisory Board, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - Advisory Board, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Steering committee memoranda, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Steering committee, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - Steering committee, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2020
    - Steering committee, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2021
    - Steering committee, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2022
    - Women's studies long range plans, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2023
    - Steering committee, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
    - Steering committee, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2024
    - Women's studies governance, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum, 1981-2008; 1.2
    The Curriculum subseries of the Administrative Materials series contains materials related to the development and revision of the curriculum of the Women's Studies Program. Included are correspondence, notes, reports, memorandums, brochures, flyers, and other materials related to individual courses, course requirements, certificate development and requirements, and other topics.
    - Certificate proposals to Curriculum committee, 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - Women's studies committee: Proposal of courses, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Courses for special topics bulletin, 1981-1983 (Box 1)
    - Syllabus for women in film house course, 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - Women's studies proposal: Original, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Syllabus for Duke/UNC women's studies course, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Asian-American women house course, 1986 (Box 1)
    - M.A.T/M.I.T., 1987-1989 (Box 1)
    - M.A.L.S., 1987-1989 (Box 1)
    - Core Curriculum, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Curriculum review committee, 1992-1999 (Box 1)
    - Graduate core courses: Permissions, wst 211, 212, 213, 214, 1994-2002 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2027
    - Graduate's guide to women's studies, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Course descriptions, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2025
    - Schiwy, Freja: Transnational dialogue: Latin American feminism, 2001 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2026
    - Course proposals, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2028
    - Curriculum materials, 2008 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2033
    - Brochures and flyers, 1980's (Box 1)
    - Brochure, 1987-1998; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Brochure, 1987 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Brochures, flyers, and reports, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Brochures, 1998-2001 (Box 1)
  - General and subject files, 1981-2002; 1.3
    The General and Subject Files subseries of the Administrative Materials series contains a wide variety of materials related to the formation, growth, operation, activities, and place within the University of the Women's Studies Program. Included are correspondence, memoranda, reports, programs, newsclippings, notes, and other materials. Topics covered include student graduation, Women's Studies certification (prior to the Women's Studies major), defining women's studies, the Women's Center, publicity around Women's Studies, and many other subjects.
    - Administrative correspondence and materials, 1983-1987; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Administrative women's network, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Administrative women's network, 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - Administrative women's network, 1997-1998 (Box 2)
    - Administrative women's network, 1998-1999 (Box 2)
    - Administrative women's network, 1999-2000 (Box 2)
    - Anniversaries brochure, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Alumni interviews: "Graduate training in women's studies", 1990 (Box 2)
    - Sallie Bingham, 1987-1995; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Book orders: Women's studies and library inventory, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Certificate earner's directory, 1992; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Certificate students, 1987-1990 (Box 20)
    - Certificate students, 1991-1992 (Box 20)
    - Continuing education, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence with administrators, 1984-1991 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1987; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1985; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1997-1998 (Box 2)
    - Curriculum committee, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Duke Directions, 1989, 1991 (Box 2)
    - External review, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Explaining women's studies, 1993-1996, undated (Box 2)
    - Fact sheet: Women's studies program, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Governance report, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Graduate certificate approval, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Graduate certificate approval, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Graduate certificate approval, 1990-1992 (Box 2)
    - Graduate certificate approval, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - Graduate certificates ceremony, 1995-1996 (Box 3)
    - Graduate groups, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Graduate groups, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Graduate reading group, 1989-1993 (Box 3)
    - 1984-1986 graduates roster (Box 3)
    - Graduate student outreach, 1993-2001 (Box 3)
    - Graduation, 1987-1989 (Box 3)
    - Graduation, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
    - Graduation: Certificate students, 1983-1986 (Box 3)
    - Graduation, 1992-1995 (Box 3)
    - Graduation, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Graduation, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Graduation, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Graduation, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Stacey Grey/Advisory council for the study of women of African decent, 2002 (Box 20)
    - Guide to graduate student research, 1990-1993 (Box 3)
    - "Hear My Story" Atlanta, Oglethorpe University, 2000-2002 (Box 3)
    - History of women's studies at Duke, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - Honorary degree: Eleanor Smeal, 1990-1991, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Honorary degree: Elly Elliot, 1998-2002 (Box 3)
    - Honorary degree: Carolyn Heilbrum, Undated (Box 20)
    - Ideas, 1997-2001 (Box 3)
    - Instructors meetings, 2000-2001 (Box 3)
    - Jean O'Barr on Women's Studies on WCHL, April 15 1994 (Box 25, Audio-cassette UA25410001-CS-0005)
    - Meetings notes and minutes, 1981-1982 (Box 3)
    - Memoranda to WS faculty, 1985-1993; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Memos to graduate students, 1987-1999 (Box 3)
    - Misuse of Mary Duke Biddle parlor, 1982 (Box 3)
    - News articles and publicity: Women's studies articles, 1980 (Box 3)
    - News articles and publicity: Chronicle and local articles on women/women's studies, 1981-1982 (Box 3)
    - News articles and publicity: Publicity/Flyers, 1981-1983 (Box 3)
    - News articles and publicity: History of women's studies at Duke, 1981-1986 (Box 3)
    - News articles and publicity: Misc. articles, 1982 (Box 3)
    - News articles and publicity: Chronicle ads, 1983 (Box 3)
    - News articles and publicity: Publicity on women's studies, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - News articles and publicity: News stories, 1984 (Box 3)
    - News articles and publicity: Faculty newsletter articles, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
    - Corky Rose, 1987-2000 (Box 3)
    - Sallie Bingham foundation, undated (Box 4)
    - Edwina Saudys, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
    - Staff meeting, 1995-2000 (Box 4)
    - Stationery/logos, 1990-1995 (Box 4)
    - Study of 1989 certificate earners and graduation day comments, Undated (Box 20)
    - Thoughts on women's studies, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
    - Trinity College board of visitors meeting (and student panel discussions), 1988-1989 (Box 4)
    - Trustees, 1984 (Box 24)
      Board of Trustees restriction until 2034.
    - Trustees, 1988 February (Box 24)
      Board of Trustees restriction until 2038.
    - 20/20: Men on Pornography, January 29 1993 (Box 25, Video-cassette UA25410001-VHS-0005)
    - Wiegman, Robyn publications, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Women imagine change legacies project development, 1994 (Box 20)
    - Women of color, 1993, 2000-2001 (Box 4)
    - Women outside the box in the nineteenth century US south: Essays by students of hist 195s.08, 2003 (Box 4)
    - Women's center, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Women's center/women's studies conversations, 1989-2001 (Box 4)
    - Women's center 10th anniversary, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Women's research center: Ford grant, undated (Box 4)
    - Women's studies resources: Workshops, films, collections, etc., 1981 (Box 4)
    - Women's Studies at Duke University: a video by Jennifer Parchesky, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 25, Video-cassette UA25410001-VHS-0001, Video-cassette UA25410001-VHS-0002)
    - WSSA initiatives, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Yale seminar "Instituting Gender", 2002 (Box 4)
    - Elizabeth (Betzy) Zung, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Financial Materials, 1981-1999; 1.4
    The Financial Materials subseries of the Administrative Materials series contains materials related to the budget, fundraising, and and financial operations of the Women's Studies Program. Included are correspondence, notes, memorandums, reports, and other materials related to the budget planning, spending, campaign strategy, donor outreach, and other financial activities of the WSP.
    - Alumnae mailing, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Budget: Women's studies budget, 1981-1983 (Box 4)
    - Budget: 1986-1987 budget materials, 1985-1986 (Box 4)
    - Budget: 1987-1988 budget materials, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
    - Budget: 1988-1989 budget materials, 1987-1988 (Box 4)
    - Budget: Budget and funding, 1999-2000 (Box 4)
    - Budget: 1998-1999 budget request (Box 4)
    - Budget: 1999-2000 budget request (Box 4)
    - Budget: Graduate budget request, 1990-1996 (Box 4)
    - Budget: TA budget, 1993-1996 (Box 4)
    - Capital campaign presentation, 1983-1984 (Box 20)
    - WS campaign budget, 1986-1988 (Box 20)
    - Capital campaign: Strategies: Campaign for women's studies, 1986-1990 (Box 4)
    - Capital campaign: Anne Scott fund, 1987-1991 (Box 4)
    - Capital campaign: Women's studies endowment list, 1989, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Capital Campaign: Teaching fund for women's studies, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
    - Capital campaign: Final plans, 1991-1992; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Capital campaigns: Phone-a-thon, 1991 (Box 4)
    - Capital campaign: Pledge cards, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Capital campaign final reports, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Case application, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Harland challenge promotion, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
    - Leads (Development), 1991 (Box 24)
      Donor restriction until 2061.
    - Women's studies samples, 1985-1988 (Box 4)
    - Sesquicentennial follow-up mailings, 1989 (Box 4)
    - MTS Solicitation (Development), 1990 (Box 24)
      Donor restriction until 2060.
    - Margaret Taylor Smith fund for women's studies, 1992-1999 (Box 4)
    - Sarah and George Taylor endowment fund for women's studies, 1997 (Box 4)
    - 150th brochure: Special mailing list, undated (Box 4)
  - Personnel Materials, 1982-2001; 1.5
    The Personnel Materials subseries of the Administrative Materials series contains materials related to the faculty, staff, and other personnel matters of the Women's Studies Program. Included are directories, correspondence, notes, memorandums, and other materials related to the faculty, administrators, staff, search for faculty members who would hold joint appointments in Womens' Studies and other disciplines, and other topics. These files do not include performance reviews or other personal employee information.
    Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
    - Armstrong, Mary, 1991-2000 (Box 4)
    - Curriculum vitae (faculty), 1982 (Box 4)
    - Faculty directory and roster, 1994, 2000, undated (Box 4)
    - Faculty retreats, 1997-2001 (Box 4)
    - Joint appointments: Announcements of joint appointments elsewhere, 1987, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Joint appointments: Complete sets of questionnaires, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Joint appointments: Correspondence to search committees, 1988 (Box 5)
    - Joint appointments: Correspondence setting up joint appointments at Duke, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
    - Joint appointments: Evaluation process, 1989-1990 (Box 24)
      Personnel restriction until 2060.
    - Joint appointments: Philosophy search committee, 1988 (Box 5)
    - Joint appointments: Political science search committee, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
    - Joint appointments: Search, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
    - Joint appointments: Search, 1991-1992 (Box 5)
    - Joint appointments: Women's studies advisory board correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
    - Managing editor of signs: Mary Wyer, 1985-1986 (Box 5)
    - Program coordinator: Cheri Siskek, 1985-1988 (Box 5)
    - Program coordinator search, 1989 (Box 5)
    - WS faculty directory, 1996-1997 (Box 20)
    - Women add-ons, 1984-1986 (Box 24)
      Personnel restriction until 2056.
  - Newsletters, 1984-2002; 1.6
    The Newsletters subseries of the Administrative Materials series consists of the newsletters published by the Women's Studies Program for students, faculty, alumni, and friends of the Program as well as drafts, correspondence, and materials about the publication of the newsletter.
    - Alumnae newsletter 8/84, 4/85, 12/85, 1984-1985 (Box 5)
    - Letter from WS newsletter, 1984-1985 (Box 5)
    - Letters from WS newsletter, 1985-1986 (Box 5)
    - Alumnae letter, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Responses to June 1986 alumnae letter (Box 5)
    - December 1986 newsletter (Box 5)
    - December 1986 responses (Box 5)
    - Fall 1990 newsletter (Box 5)
    - January 1991 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Fall 1991 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Winter 1992 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Fall 1992 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Spring 1992 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Winter 1993 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Spring 1993 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Fall 1993 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Winter 1994 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Spring 1994 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Fall 1994 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Winter 1995 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Spring 1995 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Fall 1995 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Winter 1997 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Winter 1998 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Spring 1998 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Fall 1998 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Winter 1999 newsletter (Box 5)
    - Spring 1999 newsletter (Box 5)